"Is There Really Pus in Milk?"
Dairy cows might normally live
for about 20 years,
but they are typically
slaughtered for hamburger
after they're just
a few years old,
when they produce less milk
and their profitability drops.
But another leading cause
of cow culling is mastitis,
udder inflammation
and infections,
which affects 99.7 percent
of all dairy operations
in the United States.
Because of the mastitis epidemic
in the U.S. dairy herd,
the dairy industry continues
to demand that American milk
retain among
the highest allowable
"somatic cell" concentration,
nearly twice as much
as the rest of the world--
750,000 cells per milliliter.
The concentration
in milk from healthy udders
should be less than 100,000.
These somatic cells are mostly
white blood cells,
so, when you get up
to around 200,000,
which is, like,
a million per teaspoon,
the udder is likely
to be infected.
So, the somatic cell counts
in the bulk milk tanks
reflect the level of infection.
Basically,
if the bulk milk tank,
which can hold
thousands of gallons,
averages 200,000, then 15
percent of the contributing cows
are likely infected.
At a concentration of 400,000,
which is more in line
with international standards,
a third of the cows
are likely infected.
And staying within the 750,000
U.S. limit for Grade A milk
could reflect that
about two thirds of the cows
are infected.
Now, somatic cells are not
synonymous with pus cells,
as has sometimes been
misleadingly suggested.
Just as normal human blood
and breast milk
contain low levels
of white blood cells,
so does milk from healthy cows.
That's something we've known
for more than a century.
The problem is that many
of our cows are not healthy.
According to the latest
national government survey,
about one in four dairy cows
in the United States
suffers from clinical mastitis,
the second leading cause
of death on dairy farms.
This is why the average somatic
cell concentration of U.S. milk
is that
of a likely infected udder,
at 204,000 cells per milliliter.
How much actual pus
does that translate to?
Although the industry doesn't
like to talk about pus cells,
the fact that pus is present
in milk from inflamed
mammary glands is a given.
But what constitutes
pus in milk?
The quote-unquote
"milk pus test" was introduced
more than a century ago.
It pooled milk
from infected cows
that was estimated to contain
up to 2.5 percent pus by volume.
And we'd really like to see
no more than, like, 0.1 percent.
So, what does 204,000
cells per milliliter,
the national U.S. average,
translate to?
That's a million cells
per teaspoon of milk.
A million cells per spoonful
sounds like a lot,
but pus is really concentrated.
So, how much pus is there
in a glass of milk?
Not much.
If you take the national average
and subtract the number
of white blood cells
you might see in normal milk,
you get about 100,000
inflammatory white blood cells
per milliliter,
or about 25 million per cup.
Then it just depends on the
cellular concentration of pus.
Although straight pus may have
80,000 cells per microliter or less,
to be conservative,
the most concentrated
I could find for straight pus
was about 150,000.
Note that's per microliter,
not per milliliter.
So, if there are about
25 million cells per cup,
and a microliter of pus
contains about 150,000 cells,
that would come out to be
about 150 microliters of pus
per glass of milk.
There are about
50 microliters in a drop,
so there'd only be a few drops
of pus per glass on average.
And you can apparently taste
the difference.
One of the major problems
associated with mastitis
is the flavor and texture
defects.
Milk with high somatic
cell counts looks the same,
but evidently doesn't smell
or taste as good.
The large amounts of pus
in mastitic milk
may be aesthetically
objectionable,
but it's important to note
this is not a food safety issue,
thanks to pasteurization.
The dairy industry emphasizes
that ingesting large amounts
of bovine white blood cells
has not been shown
to be harmful.
No matter how inflamed
and infected udders get,
the pus gets cooked.
But just as parents may not
want to feed their children
fecal bacteria in meat,
even if it's
irradiated fecal bacteria,
as the director of the
Food Policy Institute put it:
"Irradiated poop won't make you
sick, but it's still poop,"
parents may not want
to have their children sip
pasteurized pus.